In the world of finance, we are often quick to forget the tragedies of the past, yet valuable
lessons are to be had by exploring their causes and effects.
After all, in the world of ever changing rules, products, and services, history is the
one constant that can guide us through the ambiguity.
So let's take a five minute history lesson on today's plane bagel.
The year is 1918, and after four years of conflict, the First World War is finally over.
America has emerged as one of the victors, and is both entered a period of economic prosperity
and cultural change known as the Roaring 20s.
Things start off pretty strongly, as the postal economy is seeing a boost.
Troops are back from the war, delayed projects are spending up again, and hey, more women
are entering the workforce, meaning that more people have a salary to spend.
And companies are looking for a piece of the money pie.
So in 1920, we see our first radio advertisement.
And it seems to be working.
Recent inventions like the back and cleaner and the electric wash machine are becoming
hot commodities.
And hey, since things are looking pretty good, the banks are giving out loans to everybody,
meaning that even more people can buy the latest and greatest gadgets.
Or you know what, everyone's getting a car too.
Henry Ford's team model to be exact, and with it, life is becoming a lot easier.
Now you can do the Charleston and Cross Town, be home for your evening smoke.
All of this is making companies very rich.
And the average American is making good money themselves.
In fact, people are starting to look for things to do with their newfound wealth.
Buy another laundry machine?
Nah, a new car, don't eat it.
Oh, wait, what about investing?
Yeah, that's it.
After all, why be rich when you can be more French?
So the stock market becomes a pretty popular practice.
And with so many people buying, investors are finding it very easy to make money on stocks.
Soon enough, everyone thinks they're 1920s Warren Buffett.
And I mean everybody.
Cooks, shoe shines, tax drivers, you name it, everyone is trading like a Wall Street
tycoon, pouring their life savings into whatever security is hot that day.
In fact, there's so much money to be made, people are taking out loans to invest even more.
And banks are probably collecting the interest.
By the way, those same banks are looking to invest more money too.
And soon enough, they begin borrowing money from customer bank accounts to buy stocks.
But since things are looking up, no one's noticing.
And overall, things are going pretty well in America financially anyway.
And as we experience flapper culture, prohibition and derives of jazz music, people are making
good money on the markets.
By 1929, America's total wealth has doubled and investments are up 218% since 1922.
In fact, stocks are rising so fast, companies are having a hard time keeping up and just
finding their stock price.
Wait, that's not good.
And hold on, production actually seems to be slowing down.
Henry's not making as many team models and people aren't buying as many things.
It looks like companies may have overestimated their growth and now wages are falling.
And all that easy tax is dead.
Well, people have taken out quite a bit and, uh oh, interest rates are starting to rise.
But wait a minute, the stock market is still up.
That doesn't see right?
Even though the economy is looking worse for wear under the hood, investors are more
less ignoring these problems and buying something as if everything were exceptional.
Sure, we see a few shakeups in close calls, but things are still largely positive and people
are still gambling on the markets.
But over time, the voice of reason is getting louder.
And investor uncertainty is increasing, which brings us to October 24th, 1929.
Black Thursday, as it's called, the theorized start of the Great Depression.
Investors have been royally spooked with headlines reading, and when markets open, they start
to sell.
And I mean sell.
12.9 million shares to be exact.
A new record.
And at opening bell, things fall 11%.
People are selling so much that price stickers can't keep up with the volume.
So people don't even know what they're selling prices.
And all of this selling is dragging the stock market down, and raising large chunks of America's
wealth.
And things are about to get worse.
While markets recover later that day, come Black Tuesday, it's an outright panic.
The Dow Jones falls 12%.
And at record, we set last Thursday, yeah, we just broke it again.
The markets lose $14 billion in one day.
Some shares are now worthless.
People have lost their life savings in Americans who borrow to invest our absolutely crushed.
And so, friends, here we are.
The Great Depression, the worst economic downturn in the history of the industrialized world.
The Dow Jones falls for another three years after this, losing 90% of its value from its
high in 1929.
And they lose their jobs as companies shut down.
And it's not just investors that are hit.
Remember that money the banks borrowed?
Well, a bunch of it is lost and the market's too.
And people are only getting back $0.10 for every dollar they had in their account.
Banks across the country shut down, and unemployment reaches its highest level in US history, 24.9%.
By this point, red lines, suit kitchens, and homelessness are common sites.
Whether you invested, borrowed money, or even just held money in a bank account, the
depression found a way to hurt you financially.
Times would be tough throughout the 1930s.
And physical intervention from Franklin D. Roosevelt would do little to boost activity.
In fact, it wouldn't be until the rise of the third Reich in Germany that we would
see end to the crisis.
You see, the Great Depression wasn't just felt in America.
Rather with recent globalization, its effects were felt around the world.
And in the darkness, we saw the rise of Hitler, who used the despair of the German people
as a rallying call.
Ultimately, leading to the creation of the Nazi Party and the start of the Second World
War in 1939.
The war created jobs in America, ironically ending one tragedy with the start of another.
Experts can't agree on why the Great Depression was as bad as it was, but the war valuable
takeaways from the hardship.
It demonstrated just how powerful the greed and alternatively the fear of the markets
can be when they get out of control, while demonstrating the destructive potential of speculation
and debt.
Laws would later be introduced to safeguard financial institutions and deposits.
Injuring this time in office, Franklin D. Roosevelt would introduce the Federal Deposit Insurance
Corporation and the Securities Exchange Commission.
He was targeted at protecting the wealth of Americans that still exists to this day.
Few are left to remember the hardships of the Depression, but we'd be foolish to forget
the lessons it provided.
After all, fear, greed and speculation are far from dead.